Jubril Joshua Juma

Email: jubril.juma@gmail.com Portfolio Summary: jubriljuma.xyz

Work Experience

I have a broad range of experiences and acquired skills from various stages of a product's lifecycle. Led 2 acquired products.

April 2018 - Present

User Experience Researcher, Google (contract with Tusen Consulting), SSA

- Currently working with the Google Go product team to provide Sub Saharan Africa user experience insights.
 - Lead the planning, recruitment, execution and reporting of qualitative research (lab / in home / diary / intercept studies & country immersions) for Google Go in SSA.
 - Support the team with quantitative studies (cohort analysis, quantitative usability testing, web / app analytics,
 A/B testing, multivariate testing, card sorting, tree testing) in LATAM, SSA and SEA
- Adhoc qualitative research (lab / intercept studies & country immersions) in SSA for Photos, Lens, Payments and Maps.

November 2016-August 2017

Founding Member / Head of Products & Operations, Verifi, Nigeria

- My team and I grew the Pay product MAU from 0-123 firms over 7 months
- Scouted and recruited the local Dev team of developers after transferring product & software development from Gigster, USA
- Setup the first 3 verification centres
- Responsible for design product strategy and AGILE execution for versions 1 3 of Verifi Core and led the split of the product into Assure and Pay by Verifi
- Our execution style was Lean-AGILE product management coupled with user-centric design.
- Was responsible for product-market fit of new products -Pay (payroll software), Assure (identity verification), and Inform (3rd party data API).

•

<u>August 2015 – February 2017</u>

Co - Founder / Products and Operations, Sangalo Limited, Nigeria

- Reduced OpEx by 65% in first 4 months
- Recruited a local operations team after transferring application development from Useful and Beautiful, South Africa
- Shipped the minimum viable product 12 weeks after of hiring a local team
- Was responsible for organisational management and planning
- Led the product team
 - o 653% increase in DAU in 6 months by using iterative design to guide product strategy e.g. user insights led to the changing product roadmap from Android/iOS apps to an integrated SMS>USSD>Web product
 - Made an 83% cut in technical budget without compromising quality of service,
 - o Deployed a Lean-Agile Hybrid Framework, Continuous Integration & Project management tools.
 - Recruited and managed a specialized team of local and remote developers,
 - o Designed and deployed stable, scalable software and server architecture,
 - o Rebuilt the core of the product to attain stability, functionality and scalability,
 - o Restructured the project into Modules; Mobile App, Web App, Marketing & PR Platform, Data Warehouse.
 - o Tech Stack: Git, JIRA, Python, PHP, Mysql, MongoDB, BASH, Bamboo, Java

May 2014 - October 2015

Product Development Manager, L5lab Limited, Nigeria

- Oversaw the development and implementation of new software products
- Was responsible for Product Marketing, Strategy, Planning and Positioning.
- Drove software product enhancements Improvements / Transformational plans.
- Products worked on include Kamdora.com, Betazoo, 440.ng, Salary.ng and Pass.ng
- Tech Stack: CodeIgniter PHP Framework, ASP.NET MVC (C#), MSSQL (CodeSmith), Git, JIRA, Bamboo, Confluence Microsoft Azure and Amazon Web Services

<u> August 2013 – May 2014</u>

Product Development Manager, 4Forty Bus Limited (an L5lab Investment), Nigeria

- Delivered consistent growth in operations and sales up till the acquisition of the company by www.Wakanow.com
- Led a successful Go-to-Market launch to acquire early adopters (MAU customer growth grew by 215%)
- Managed and developed the life cycle of 3 products- BookingSync, Oya.com.ng and WebBooking

Other Activities

2015-Present UX Masterclass organiser and faciliatator

2014-Present Early stage startup investment and advisory; Alizarin Crimson Limited, and PRISE Limited, Shuttlers.ng,

BeatTraffik, Abee's Place, JAL Fund

2017 UX and PM Mentor, <u>www.CodeMentor.com</u>, Remote

2015 iDEA GEM Mentor, iDEA Hub, Lagos, Nigeria

2009 - 2015 Volunteer (multiple sales and marketing roles), AIESEC, Nigeria

Soft Skills Summary

Venture Development | Private Equity | Portfolio Management | Investment Analysis | Productivity & Efficiency Improvements | Organisational Management & Planning | PMP and AGILE (SCRUM/Kanban/Lean/XP) | UX & UI Design | Web Site Analytics | Prototyping with Invision and Proto.io | Wireframing | Information Architecture (IA) | User Research and Testing | Requirements Definition | HTML/XHTML | CSS3 | JavaScript/jQuery | PHP | Photoshop | Sketch | Illustrator | Bootstrap 2 and 3 | HTML 5 Boilerplate | Wordpress | Visual Design | Applications Development | Blockchain/ Distributed Ledger PM

Education

Formal

2009 - 2015 B. Sc., Genetics and Biotechnology, University of Calabar, Calabar, Nigeria

Short Courses

2017 Introduction to Hyperledger and other Distributed Ledger Technologies (Linux Foundation)

2016 Investment Management (University of Geneva, Switzerland)

Human - Computer Interaction Design (University of California, San Diego)

2015 HTML 5

CSS3

2014 Firm and Corporate Business Strategy (Darden Business School, Virginia)

Lean Start-up Methodology

User Experience and Interactive Design

AGILE Methodologies (SCRUM/Kanban/Lean/XP)

Python

Project Management Introductory Finance

New Venture / Enterprise Development

2013 Google Analytics Professional Certified

2013 Associate Degree, Information Risk Management, University of Washington,

Washington DC, USA

Background

While in university, I started volunteering for sales / business development roles with AIESEC to build sales and leadership experience. During the 2013 school strike, I got a role at a startup (4Forty Bus limited) which quickly evolved into a product manager role until it got acquired by Wakanow.com. I was offered a product manager role with the investing company, L5lab, with whom I worked part-time until I graduated from school in 2015. This to me was like a second university major, because I learnt a lot from the team and was able to act upon my learnings within the 1 year+ that I was with L5lab. When I graduated from school I joined a football social network as a co - founder until it got acquired by iConcepts limited, and then founded another project (Verifi.ng) with 3 co - founders to solve the people data problem in Nigeria. This is still an ongoing project, however, I stepped away from the day - to - day operations due to personal reasons. Currently, I help cross functional teams see the the world and "that" product through the eyes of the user to allow them build sustainable products. I am a very strong self-starter and a lover of data / data backed decision making.